oh in the middle uh
well hello and welcome to wasabi
research club number
i don't know
well today we will be
37 right today i'm talking
27 okay
today we will be talking about uh amount
organization in coinjoin transactions
so that is all about sub transactions
and input to output mapping and the
knobsack paper
this goes all the way back to wasabi
research club number one where we
covered the knobs paper in detail and
today we will kind of rehash all the
things that we learned in the meantime
and hopefully uh figure out some
interesting ways of how to use this in
wasabi 2.0
so to start this out with you well what
do you think why is this an important
question to talk about in the first
place
uh yeah so
basically
in the like when we started talking
about coinjoins um we i mean i wasn't
around back then but like everybody was
kind of assuming um at first uh there
would be equal amounts
uh and then uh we discovered uh when
that
um
you know when you when you relax that
assumption which is already should
should look a little bit fishy
uh actually in practice um it it's uh
even worse than people expected uh so
we're going to look at the paper in in a
bit more detail look at some of their
simulation results and we can kind of
begin to to to maybe quantify
under their assumptions their modeling
assumptions um like
just how good or bad it is
uh but it's i mean even though the
assumptions are maybe not so realistic
it's uh it's still very instructive and
of course there's the famous shared coin
story
um so
um
[Music]
conservative implementations have have
gone for equal amount outputs uh joint
market wasabi samurai they all
kind of apply this approach
and the knapsack paper showed how
you can
in certain cases
uh you can make payments from coin
joints
where
the
linkage between the payment amount and
the inputs
um
is is made more more ambiguous more
private but it's it's designed
with that specific use case
uh in mind and
um
there's some limitations in the proposed
algorithms there's also is issues with
how it handles the change
so it's it's like it's not a complete
story um the the thing that they propose
in the paper
but i think actually the paper's main
contribution is the model that they use
to analyze um the performance of their
algorithms
so this model is uh
quite precise it's um
i think it describes the privacy problem
in a very general and very powerful way
and it's uh general enough to take into
account um
uh equal amounts or
um
uh arbitrary amounts
uh and yeah the goal for today is kind
of establish a baseline for um
like how how do you understand
uh how do you analyze situations with
this model um
and how how can we uh generalize it a
little bit more so that it uh works uh
like in a real setting with fees and
stuff like that which was not uh
taken into account in the paper that's
that's basically the goal
um
okay let me
i'm gonna share my screen and hand it
back to
max or rafe
which one of you wants to go
i think one one thing to highlight is
that in wasabi
we kind of took the easy way of just
using the standard amount denominations
and one of the reasons for that was
because the charmian
blind signature coin join algorithm
that at the cryptographic layer only
provide
privacy guarantees
if all participants have standard
denomination outputs right so there was
a
limitation of standard denomination
outputs already on the cryptographic
layer so we just stuck with that and
only guarantee privacy for those
standard denominations
but that of course leaves the problem of
multiple denominations and change and
all of that stuff uh and
the crucial difference and why we bring
this topic up now again is because with
wabi-sabi on the cryptographic layer we
no longer have a privacy leak with uh
equal
or with the amount of denominations so
we have privacy guarantees on the
protocol layer even for
not standard denominations just regular
payment amounts
and that
that means we can now actually
experiment and go for a more optimal
solution
that hopefully also enables the payments
inside the coin joint which would be
best
so unless anyone else has a note
you will give us an overview
okay so i guess i'll go
um
okay so i think i already gave
most of the overview
um
i guess one thing that's um
[Music]
like the the next logical step is to go
through um okay what what
how
much of bitcoin do you need to
understand to kind of follow through
this conversation
um so
like bitcoin has a very complicated
system there's the network layer there's
the cryptography there's uh so uh most
of that uh we don't really need for
today uh we might mentioning it mention
it in passing but we can uh
kind of pretend
uh that it's just a giant spreadsheet
that magically works in in the right way
and there's no consensus problem and
um like the there's no bitcoin script
it's just like some
magic
like there's a
an owner column in in our spreadsheet
and uh uh based on the owner column um
like that's
the system somehow magically guarantees
that all authorized transactions are
allowed to be made so i've made a small
visual aid let me see if i can find the
url
[Music]
um okay so
we can uh uh kind of imagine at genesis
time
like maybe this row didn't exist
there was just this one coin
uh so what a point for our purposes
today uh it's something that
uh comes into existence at a specific
transaction and we're just gonna number
those or whatever we don't even care
about transaction ids
uh it's got an amount um
[Music]
and uh again it's it's got some sort of
owner field which is you know just
abstracting away all the details of
bitcoin script and we also put down the
transaction number in which it was so
uh the way mining works uh for our
purposes is every several minutes on on
average every 10 minutes or so
a new coin magically appears and one of
the miners uh appears in this column
um and we kind of like this is
pseudonymous here right like
we don't really know who who did this we
can only presume um
okay so uh looking at some of uh
bitcoin's uh real history
there we go
uh
i think that's a bit more reasonable so
i put in some of the first uh
transactions
from the like the actual bitcoin
blockchain uh it's the genesis block uh
this is like the first coinbase
transaction
uh and this is transaction number nine
which uh famously was used uh uh how
finney described uh in a bitcoin uh talk
post
um how uh he was the recipient of the
the first uh transaction
um
here i think
so um
we can kind of use this as a way to like
really understand what
like what are the implications of of the
way that the blockchain is structured by
by looking at this uh in terms of the
coins so uh if transaction number nine
here created a coin um and uh
later we see that transaction number 171
which we know based on the forum post
like 10 of which went to hal and 40 of
which went to satoshi or we presume it
went to satoshi
uh this is also how we know that this
coin belonged to satoshi and uh just to
be clear what the colors denote here uh
it's just the the groupings of the
outputs of an individual transaction so
it's it's the same color coding is here
um
[Music]
so
um we can
look at the the
how things continue right if we look at
satoshi's output or satoshi's presumed
output
uh this is a transaction that was
confirmed
in block uh
uh and it has um
another
10 bitcoin output and a 30 bitcoin
output now now here we
already like we don't really know uh
what was going on we we can no longer
interpret these numbers um in as clear a
way
but obviously like as we start filling
in
more and more information about this
column and and start you know making
connections between these columns uh
like i hope it's self evident even to
somebody who doesn't really understand
how the coin works uh on a technical
level
um that there's a sort of paper trail
being recorded um
okay so um
yeah uh i think
that
more or less covers it
so um
[Music]
yeah that's that's our model for today
um
and um
uh
yeah i think at this point i wanna uh
ask uh rayford or max is going to take
over and uh
uh like lets us through the the next
sections and uh um uh because because uh
i'm uh
i don't
want to like just take over and and
speak into into the void
yeah i mean like
i i really don't have like anything yet
on my mind about this i was reading
through your notes
and yeah i didn't get to the end of it
but yeah
i mean it all makes sense
at least for now
we're
uh
we don't we're not supposed to make it
to the end i think today uh but like
basically
um
like uh
like we're at this section here so um
uh
i guess
uh please
tell me where to scroll and kind of like
uh like talked before the thing like
make it a performance for for the
youtube
i think one thing to consider next is
uh what transaction privacy and
transaction surveillance this is about
so how in your simplified
model
how do you look at these two things
um yep uh
so
like should i do you wanna like
poke through the example some more or do
you wanna like go through the notes step
by step or
uh like the the reason i'm struggling
and the reason i asked for help uh
before is is basically
um
i've i've been like too immersed in this
stuff and um i
have a difficult time not jumping ahead
so
in order to make this more accessible to
a general audience
like i need help from from
youtube so let's let's take for example
uh just the
consolidation of multiple coins in a
transaction
how does that look in your model
okay so we can just invent an example
here uh let's just copy
uh or we can do this on this
third ticket yes
okay so
how out um so let's say satoshi did
something else uh and the first thing
uh was i don't know
mine another coin
so that would look something like
this i guess
uh
and for now this would also be unspent
um
sorry this is bugging me
oh
they are
um so now satoshi has two coins
so transaction three
uh might be
uh
consolidating them into a single one
and in the same operation
the number three would be
indicated here and these rows would be
marked unspendable so
i don't know we can cross them out or
something
so that that would be a consolidation
okay so here on the spreadsheet right if
you want to generate a coin you write on
the
left side the number of the funding
transaction and the amount of the output
of that transaction into the owner is
and then when you want to make a
spending transaction
uh you
choose which currently unspent coin is
as suitable
so you do that by checking unspent in
the d column
and then writing the
number of transaction there which is in
our case three and that denotes the
inputs of this transaction
um
while then in column b and row five
the amount is 100 so that's the
oh the output amount of this transaction
uh it's the sum of the two inputs
consolidated 50 plus 50.
yes
and if we want to do the opposite
suppose uh now 75 needs to be sent
somewhere uh right or maybe uh we can
just show what would have happened if
satoshi would have needed to spend 75 so
there would be another
output of transaction three here for the
remainder the remain uh
remainder
i cannot spell
yes so here we have a transaction
spending two inputs
and
in line three and line four
and creating two outputs in line five
and line six column b
exactly
and i guess
we can now show okay let's imagine that
this was uh
a payment sent to somebody
and this was the change so what does it
look like if uh satoshi then makes
another payment
um so
maybe it would be something like this
transaction 4 sends uh 15
to
something else
third person
and then so this is also unspent for now
but in order to do this this coin no
longer belongs to satoshi so has to be
this one
so let's mark that
and then this also has a a change output
and
like as we can see there's
it's not directly obvious that this
payment and this payment
can be linked somehow
but if we follow
uh
the transaction numbers we can we can
see
uh how everything kind of hooks up
and can be threaded together
okay so this is helpful for us in a
privacy analysis
because we can
basically easily check
whichever
number of the funding transaction equals
the number of the spending transaction
and
that just means there's some
linkage
in the
in these two transactions
yes and and that's precisely what we
call the transaction graph right so
uh in mathematics a graph or a network
is a set of vertices or points or nodes
uh which are connected by edges
uh there's a few ways of thinking of uh
like
formally modeling the transaction graph
as a graph
it's maybe a little tricky but like
um
maybe the simplest way is you can think
of uh
coins individual outputs as uh nodes on
the graph and they connect with edges to
uh different nodes that are transaction
notes that they kind of bind together
stuff and then new coin nodes come out
of uh transaction nodes so
like that that's uh
called a bipartite graph and i think
that's the first way in which the the
bitcoin graph was the bitcoin
transaction graph was kind of visualized
in the in the very first papers
and there's of course this common input
ownership hiristic granted that's an
assumption that if there are multiple
coins being spent in the input of a
transaction
that these belong to the same person
now does your simplified way of looking
at things
does that help us with that assumption
um
i mean so
the like
this heuristic uh so just for a bit of
history uh like this both heuristics
were kind of implied in the paper as was
the address reuse constraints so address
reuse in this case
has to do with how we fill in this
column so we've kind of ignored that
detail which was uh very important
especially in the early ages
but
the uh like the the heuristics here so
um
let's look at this number right like why
do we assume that the 75 went to
somebody else and the 25 is what went to
satoshi
well that's because if the 25 was the
payment amount then why would you have
needed to use two coins to make that
payment
um
so
these heuristics um i mean they
uh
directly apply to
um to to our model today uh it's only
the address reuse issue that's kind of
uh
abstracted over
okay and so then where do joints come
into play
um
okay so
uh do you wanna have a have a crackhead
explaining
or
sure so
i guess the gist of it is
is the bitcoin or coin joints are
collaborative bitcoin transactions and
so that multiple users come together and
provide multiple inputs to a single
transaction
so this just by definition breaks this
common input ownership heuristic which
says that all inputs of a transaction
belong only to one user
but with a coin join by definitions
there are many users owning each some
coins in this large collaborative
transaction
and
they also control many outputs
i don't think that that's in the
definition of coinjoin i think the coin
joint definition is solely on the
consolidation of inputs with many users
um and in theory you could have a coin
joint with one output you know paying
one entity that would be like a batch
payment of many users to one service
provider
for example
but
more likely each of these users is going
to pay
either to
different merchants or to himself right
so a mix to yourself
and
in both of these use cases then we have
multiple
users controlling the inputs and
multiple users controlling the outputs
and
yeah the question is now is this an
obvious break of this assumption uh of
the common input ownership heuristic um
which in the case of previous wasabi 1.0
conjoints and probably also wasabi 2.0
coin choice coin joints this is not the
case so an outside observer can can tell
that it's very likely that this
transaction was created by multiple
users and not just by one
whereas for example pay joins
are a type of coin join where only two
users consolidate their their points in
a way that it's arguably difficult to
find out that this is in fact two people
consolidating their coins and many would
assume that it's one person
i think those were excellent points um
anybody else have anything to add um
okay so
um
thinking about how we
analyze
uh just to start
simple uh equal amount
coin joints um
so we
there's a a bit of a nuance here which
is that
we want to separate the discussion
between what happens inside of a
transaction and what happens like
between transactions uh with regards to
anonymity
so
in order to kind of um analyze this uh
problem with with different like
theoretical tools um like focusing in on
kind of where it all begins uh
uh like we um
let's talk about the
how equal amount coin joints can kind of
exist in a uh
in in a wider mix um so
uh
like the the problem with coin joints uh
scaling naively is that
the queen transactions are size limited
so there's uh
uh
a hundred thousand virtual bytes uh or
400 000 weight units and there's a a few
bytes of overhead but other than that
it's all uh like just the inputs and
outputs
and
um
if you look at it naively
this would suggest so at uh
like
roughly 100 bytes for a single input and
a single
output we would be limited to about a
thousand uh input output pairs in kind
of uh a mixie coin joint transaction
that
everybody has the same denomination
going in everybody has the same
denomination going out
maybe the input denomination and the
opposite denomination are not the same
uh but like that's kind of the the
theoretical scaling maximum of like how
how big an anonymity set can you create
in a single bitcoin transaction
uh and this seems quite limited so um
uh yeah uh anybody want to like
uh
talk a little about a little bit about
uh the intuitions for um like how
uh anonymity sets can uh uh
like spread uh across transactions uh
and uh inherit between coins
i mean just uh in a simply way uh
like
yeah you have a limited set of anonymity
that you can gain from a one transaction
but whenever you can like uh
connect these different uh for example
like coin joint transactions
you might be able to get much more
anonymity for your coins
because of the like
yeah interoperability of these different
rounds
and just to highlight that because block
space is limited and transaction size is
limited
there is a
natural bound to how large the anonymity
sites can get
and that means that we need to carefully
allocate the scarce resource
especially if you want to provide a high
quality service of controlling
coordination then everyone will favor to
be in a high quality coordinated coin
join that is well optimized and privacy
preserving in all regards
um
of course that's assuming that there is
high demand for block space and that we
actually need to allocate that resource
carefully but i guess in any polish case
scenario for bitcoin that's that's gonna
be the case so that's what we're
building for
maybe just as an example like uh even if
you get for example like and i think
it's just a general trend that we tend
to optimize for block efficiency
even at quite a cost
yeah and like if for example you have
only like hundred percent participants
in a coin joint round
uh yeah you have like anonymity set
hundred if yeah if they all have like an
equal output uh denomination but if for
example 50 of them goes on and mix in
another round with 50 new different
participants
the original ones who liked 50 who
didn't mix they also will benefit for
the other 50 who did remix
so it kind of like connects these two
rounds and like it just multiplies the
anonymity set whenever you can like
connect these different rounds
yes and in the ideal case instead of 50
users going into one round and 50 users
going into another round
which would uh
be very slow growth rate ideally every
user would go into a separate round if
they're going to remix
that would be the the quickest way in
which this uh kind of additive sorry
multiplicative effect uh
so from from the point of view of an
individual coin
or an individual allocation of funds
uh tracing through the mixing graph
um
the
direct
uh anonymity set
accumulation is additive right every
transaction there's a number of other
inputs
and outputs that may be interchangeable
with your input or your output from this
transaction and if you keep going well
now your your coin that's already a
little bit private uh becomes an input
into the next one and and create creates
a new coin
uh which has a higher score so that's
that's an additive process but if you
uh estimate how
good it could get in the best case
uh well maybe there's a uh an
exponentially growing number of uh past
coins kind of in your history
uh and like rafe said um
uh an exponentially growing and
unbounded uh number of uh coins uh
possibly in your uh future history
uh in like a potential future history
like a history that
is not actually true
something that some other user did but
which
uh you have plausible deniability right
now it could have been your coin that
went into that mix and therefore
for all anybody knows you could be still
mixing until this day kinda
um
and uh
i think greg maxwell already described
in the
bitcoin talk post um
kind of what's what's the optimal
structure for this so
uh this comes from uh like network uh
theory uh
uh communications stuff so um
if we have uh
like in in kind of the the base case uh
just this uh
four user transaction
uh four inputs going in for outputs
going out
and we compare it with this
uh graph of four uh two input two output
transactions
uh again with the same idealization that
there's no fees or anything yet so
um
hopefully it's it's kind of obvious that
these two graphs are uh equivalent um
and if you try and scale this to higher
numbers and try and
uh minimize the total number of edges or
the total number of transactions or the
like the total number of uh
inputs or outputs per transaction every
one of these parameters uh affect things
uh a little bit differently
uh and in general uh like this is oh
wait i'm in dark mode so this is gonna
be ugly but um
the wikipedia page on uh interconnection
networks uh and switching networks
uh shows uh a few classic examples and i
think the one uh
maxwell was describing is the class
network which is i think always three
stages yeah and um
okay so so
if you're able to plan like in
in advance you could make rounds of
potentially
as many users as would fit in a block or
even several blocks
uh like you don't need to do an equal
amount coinjoin only in the space of a
single transaction uh in order to
benefit from
the same kind of approach to privacy
this is what samurai does with uh their
whirlpool stuff um like they have
five participant coin joints where two
of the inputs pay for the fees and the
three of the inputs are outputs from
previous transactions and all of the
outputs are identical
so then they try and build a transaction
graph where
because of this homogeneity on both
sides uh right or partial homogeneity on
both sides of the transaction and
complete homogeneity on the output side
um you you kind of uh get large privacy
sets
sorry large anonymity sets uh even if
the individual transactions are not very
large uh whereas wasabi takes a uh
currently takes a little bit of a
different approach
okay so
i hope it's obvious
this doesn't really
um
work with uh uh unless you have this uh
standardization of the amounts right
like
if the standardization is different
between transactions
um or uh right you you you can still
standardize
uh like wasabi does today um
there's a denomination for the round and
everybody in that round uses that
denomination but
uh the way it relates to the
denomination of other rounds is um
it slowly varies over time uh decreasing
slightly so that uh
users can
mix without consolidating with new coins
uh even though in reality we have to
account for the fees
um
[Music]
okay so um
yeah uh anybody want to talk about like
how does this break down uh when when
you start dealing with uh arbitrary
amounts um
i mean
i think yeah like
by kind of like using the or like
applying the knapsackiness to the the
output amounts you can
at least hide something in there uh like
you can have multiple different
denominations
already in that way but you're jumping
ahead
oh okay
uh so like uh
basically um
[Music]
what i'm kind of going for
is
uh
because transactions are quite large but
not that large
if you start allowing i mean there's uh
between
uh one satoshi and 10 bitcoin there's a
billion different possible values
and uh if you can only have up to a
thousand
inputs and outputs under the like the
most constrained situation so
in reality
only up to several hundreds of inputs
and probably every user is going to have
several inputs and several outputs and
right that there's all these
things that that kind of
make it
look like um
maybe even in the average case
there will still be for for most values
there will be sufficient privacy if you
do nothing to kind of
uh control the amounts but
um
if if like if you don't make an effort
to open up this
interconnection between transactions
um
it's not really going to happen on its
own uh it's going to happen to to kind
of a limited extent so
and the kind of the good news is if you
do give it an opportunity
uh well
network theory kind of tells you that
you
don't
you don't need very much right in
a community graph
so if you like
kind of uh look at all the different
owners of the coins as nodes on a graph
and
whether or not they've mixed with each
other is uh like the the connectivity of
this
um typically in community networks you
have a strongly connected component that
almost everybody on the graph is uh
hooked up to and
uh through that everybody can reach
everybody else and um
what you need for for that to happen say
in a randomly constructed graph is just
to control the no degree
and make it
high enough
for us we're working in a slightly
different setting because like we don't
really have a community graph we have a
transaction graph which um
uh kind of evolves differently over time
um
but still the um
the
logic of
if you make sure that there's an
opportunity and at least some of the
time
you kind of um
build in a structure that's
kind of like this
then uh even if it's only two inputs in
and two inputs out but you have this
like
ever expanding uh right if if
two standard denomination inputs for
each transaction are coming in from a
coin join and two
uh are
going
into a coin join uh maybe there's more
maybe there's additional denominations
or or even just one
and and one
uh right uh
uh as long as there's at least one other
identical coin that maybe doesn't come
from a coin join and another that maybe
doesn't go to a coin joint but one of
them did
if this
connectivity uh
is is uh
happening
uh just enough there's a kind of
transition point
where now you go from anonymity sets
that scale with the size of the
transaction
uh or with the size of a coin's history
right your mixing depth
and you get anonymity sets that scale
with the um
like the overall size of the mix graph
uh in both directions
um
i think i overdid the technical uh
so
anyway let's move on
but it's it's it's very interesting and
i guess one question that i have is
where is the trade-off from having
many small coin joints to having one
larger coin join
uh like
is there some point where or or how do
you even measure that trade-off
so
maybe i'm kind of skipping ahead here
but um the
the condition that i'm describing
here
um this is only for a single
denomination and so i think the the
kind of the best scale for transactions
is to have them as small as possible for
reliability and ux reasons
so long as we are actually able to
accomplish
this with a high enough degree right so
for the reasonable range of values the
reasonably popular denominations uh
hopefully we have
at least several equal amount outputs at
least one of which goes into another
coin transaction and better yet
we have some inputs
as well and if every denomination uh
satisfies this
then we basically have unrestricted
growth of the anonymity sets of every
denomination separately
but because the denominations correspond
with each other as um
like preferred value series or powers of
a certain base
um
they
uh
naturally will lend themselves to the
construction of arbitrary amounts even
with a small number of representative
equal amounts so this
further means that the chance that an
arbitrary amount input or an arbitrary
amount output
would be interchangeable with one of the
these representatives of the
uh equal groups
that would be sufficiently high that we
can actually have robust anonymity for
uh arbitrary values as well directly in
the transaction
uh this would mean that we could do safe
batch payments and stuff like that
um
how you actually
uh
yeah i i mean again i'm kind of jumping
ahead so like uh here below uh where
we're supposed to like address exactly
how it arises due to the sub transaction
model
um
does that uh
like clear things up um like it's it's
about how these two parts of the
transactions relate to each other that
kind of determines what is the right
scale so
arguably for equal amount coin joins if
you can ensure that homogeneity the
um
the correct size is two
uh and then you uh you always have like
chains of pairwise transactions maybe at
that point the like the unlock time
inversion overhead um kind of becomes a
bit more wasteful but
in principle the smaller the transaction
the fewer people it it involves the
higher the reliability and the better
the ux
um you could still even in the case of
just two users as long as the mix depth
is
more than one on average
um like you should still have a strongly
connected component where uh the
anonymity set is is unbounded
unfortunately that can't really work
because of fees but uh samurai has made
it work for five users
i
i guess one
one additional question would be that
where does the privacy come from here is
it from the equal denomination or from
the history of the coin
in a sense that what if i have an
unmixed coin
and i just create a setup transaction
where i generate equal denomination
outputs
and then later i register those
self-created outputs that are standard
denomination in the coin joint is there
any benefit to that
there is in the sense that now there's a
chance that you gain ambiguity on the
input side as well like exactly the same
analysis that we do here on the outside
because normally we expect the input
amounts to be arbitrary and it's it's
only by coincidence that maybe we have
equal outputs
um but exactly the same analysis uh
applies to both sides so uh in principle
when you have equal amount inputs uh
it's exactly the same kind of privacy as
we have today with uh german market with
wasabi uh et cetera so
um
i guess
[Music]
and
more generally it's both right you you
need both you need to have
some degree of equal amount outputs
inside of the transaction otherwise this
inheritance doesn't even
come into play right like if you don't
have this local property that these two
outputs are identical and these two
inputs are identical
uh or or something similar to that where
there's
multiple ways of interpreting this data
and you need some sort of external
information to tell you
um
how to distinguish these two
so
if you
ensure that in a certain way here at the
local level then
and it holds on
uh different related transactions then
this means that there is an emergent uh
kind of
a combination of the the like the the
inheritance of privacy emerges between
the transactions right like we know that
this input
is not like this input
it's better because this input
could have come from either this input
or this input
and this input
and this input are just as good each one
of these contributes
to prior
coins
not just
uh like the the
interchangeability here where they enter
the transaction
um
so
yeah you you you cannot really have
inheritance without some sort of
regularity at least going back into the
history
but if you
insure it on both sides of a transaction
then it can kind of grow
backwards as well as forwards and the
forward growing uh anonymity set
again is potentially unbounded because
uh it's all the transactions are going
to happen
um
and uh
um and and yeah that this doesn't really
arise unless you have uh the the basic
building block of of uh fundamental
ambiguity uh kind of at the bottom
okay i think we've uh
um
so how do we move this to the
multi-sub transaction
model so with multiple denominations and
such
no no no no no i mean
this is a later step right like this is
a much later step what we were talking
about i mean
okay so just to summarize the
conversation where remixes are important
and maybe the older the
remix utxo is the better the
connectivity of the graph is
but
how do we
create the transactions right that's the
that's the
next step that's the immediate question
here
yes the purpose of this discussion is
basically um like it's all it's clear to
us how we gain
privacy here
so
um the point of this is to point out
that the in in this structure
the privacy is potentially unbounded but
uh has this kind of uh
bifurcating behavior right if you go
above a certain critical point
then you can tap into that unbounded
anonymity set but if you go below then
it it doesn't
it doesn't experience that
multiplicative growth that uh rafe was
talking about it's only uh
an additive growth
so um
the
basically the observation is that this
is where the the
it
it appears that the most uh
robust kind of uh uh non-uh disjoint
privacy right so coin swap would be even
more private but if we're
restricting to the
um
situation where
um the there's still a history shared
between coins
then this is basically as good as we can
get
and um i wanted to point out that it's
actually a
fairly easy property to obtain
uh based on the the network theory stuff
right so if we have um
uh ambiguity
uh
in terms of equal amount outputs
uh existing inside of transactions
uh so this this can be a uh like this
two into out can be
its own standalone transaction or it can
appear as part of a larger transaction
um and if we have this kind of like
connectivity not idealized like here but
random connectivity and all we need to
do is basically
make the average
degree uh higher than one so
as long as uh some of the time some of
the users are remixing
then uh we should be able to achieve
that
uh without doing anything more so this
means we can set aside the entire
discussion about interconnectivity
uh and and uh re-specify it uh like in
terms of a local property so i think we
actually discussed all this stuff in the
notes
um
[Music]
but yeah like the the idea is like now
that we understand how
everything
exists outside of the
like
in between the transactions
we can focus
on the inter transaction structure and
kind of take this
idea that
like as as a requirement for good
privacy
uh we need to still use some um like
equal amount coinjoins as the basic
building block
um and we want to have uh like that
degree of uh of remixing that that would
ensure uh
that most coins end up on the strongly
connected component of the graph
okay so how
okay so for that we're let's dive into
the actual sub transaction model so
um
i can
bring up the paper
um
or no it's not time for that yet so
i guess let's let's through some of
these uh
basic definitions for mainly for
completeness so
uh we're interested here in sets and
multisets and we don't need the like the
general
uh definition for um our purposes we can
just think of sets as numbers not like a
general mathematical thing so it's just
an unordered collection of numbers or of
uh
uh individual coins which we can
identify with numbers right so we we can
like if we want to talk about a set of
coins we can just give them a numbering
and then say like this is a list of
coins
and when we say a set or a multiset it
should be clear that this is different
from a list
because a list inherently has
order in it whereas a set does not
uh the difference between a set and a
multi-set is that sets uh can only
contain or not contain an element uh
either something is a member or is not
whereas multi-sets allow uh an element
to appear multiple times so it's kind of
uh you you count uh zero or more times
uh for every element or one or more
times
uh but multisets are still not ordered
so uh lists are kind of like uh
what you get when you or lists with
repetition is what you get when you
impose an order on a multiset and uh
lists without repetition is what you get
when you impose an order on a set
um
okay so
also just to keep things kind of um
like
it might get confusing
like sometimes we care
about individual coins being unique
right like this is coin number 43 or
something and it's different than coin
number 47 which is uh just after it in
the blockchain or something
um at other times we want to talk about
coins as if they are only
the number amount so this is why we need
both sets and multisets right generally
we're going to be thinking about
sets of unique coins or multi sets of
amounts that correspond to each other
um
uh so this is just uh yeah uh to to
hopefully
keep those um
cleared up uh
the next concept we need is that of
partition so
sets can have subsets
so a subset is just
another set which contains
some of the elements of the other set
if a is a subset of of b
then for every element in a
let's call it x
x is also in b
so
we can talk about the set of all
possible subsets
um of uh
a set and that's called the power set
and we can also talk about um
kind of slicing a set
into
what are called disjoint subsets so
these are subsets that uh don't share
any elements right so in the power set
there is some overlap right like if we
have
the set one two three
uh then the set two three and the set
one two um those are both subsets of one
two three
a partition is uh where we divide up the
item so that each one goes into a unique
subset called a part
so um
this would be something like putting one
into its own part
and two and three into a separate part
or maybe having uh each one of the
values uh as a separate part uh or
another partition is just the set itself
so those are
subsets and partitions of sets
uh any questions so far it's kind of
like i know it's it's boring and tedious
but um it's
the these definitions are kind of
required for uh
understanding the the paper uh in detail
and uh
um
okay so moving on what are sub
transactions so um let me quickly switch
to share
actually um i think i'll open it in
another tab that way
um
okay
has everybody donated to scihab
okay so uh what is a sub transaction so
i think they uh defined this in section
four
um
let's read through this um
a little bit carefully so a coinjoin
transaction t
is
i o and v
so the inputs are i
uh
outputs are o
um
and there's a function assigning uh
values right so these are unique coins
and and they're representing
with this uh v function
uh a mapping from coins to their amount
so that's kind of like uh
a funny way of uh of saying that that
this is a unique it's a set of like
unique coins
uh but we also keep the kind of the
multi-set view um
available inside of this function
okay so
there's a condition here so as i say as
we do not consider fees the sum value of
all input coins must be equal to the sum
value of all alpha coins so for every
coin in the transaction
i we look at the value we add those all
up together and they're they're saying
that this has to be
equal
we know that that's not the case because
um it's no longer possible to broadcast
uh transactions with zero fees like
hal and satoshi's transaction that we
saw earlier
um and we also know that this is not how
the real world coin joint services
actually work all three of them
utilize fees uh mining fees and
coordinator fees
so um
or maker fees in joint markets case so
uh like this is um
uh yeah just bear that in mind we're
gonna have to like generalize this
um
so
[Music]
a coin joint transaction consists of
sub-transactions
uh each consisting of inputs and outputs
right so we identify
uh by k
uh
the like unique part
and then we have a subset of the inputs
and a subset of the outputs
uh which we associate with this
um
so uh this is a partition that's
basically what they're they're saying um
and um
right this is the the condition here uh
uh the disjointness
uh and secondly
um
[Music]
they are saying that for every
sub-transaction
the sum condition must also hold so it's
not just for the transaction as a whole
but it's for every sub-transaction in
isolation
um
so this uh idea of having uh a sorry
sorry uh so uh a partition is a sub
transaction mapping it's uh a sub
transaction is a part uh
uh that that satisfies this condition a
sub transaction mapping is a partition
of the set of inputs and outputs of the
transaction
uh and and we've kind of been thinking
like before i introduced uh partitions
of a set whereas here they have two
separate sets
so let's talk about that detail uh in a
little bit uh more clarity so
it's not just that we're slicing the
inputs and outputs into like different
groups we're slicing the inputs and
outputs separately we're partitioning
the inputs and outputs separately and
then we're defining a mapping between
every part of the
input partition and every part of the
output partition so also this means that
the number of parts in each partition
have to be the same
so this is kind of a more
complicated constraint
it's entirely equivalent to saying like
let's just think of all inputs and all
outputs as a single set
and say that we need to partition things
uh but every part has to have at least
one input and at least one output uh
that would that would be
an equivalent way of
defining sub transaction mappings
um
maybe a more intuitive one but this one
is a little bit more precise and even
though it seems more complicated we'll
see that it's
it really helps with the analysis later
um
is everyone with me so far
yes
yeah
okay so uh we know what setup
transactions are we know so what sub
transaction mappings are
um
the last
kind of important thing here is uh
um
yeah so
uh first of all they point out that
there's at least
one
uh
valid sub transaction mapping
uh right because we know that there's uh
uh in the trivial case like if it was a
single user transaction then there's one
part uh
and uh
so so a trivial solution always exists
and uh also we know that like bitcoin
transactions are the actions of actual
users that actually
uh we can attribute things to them so um
we we know that there's at least one
true way in which even a coin joint
transaction happened it's just that if
the coin join is uh actually privacy
preserving uh then that mapping should
not be observable to any one entity
every participant in the transaction
only knows about their coins and
if there's any coordination
uh then like
they they they should not know uh either
uh and join market it's a little bit
different because in in that case the
taker is also coordinating the
transaction and the taker is the one
buying the privacy so
uh even though one entity does know the
full mapping
uh that doesn't violate the the
privacy assumptions because uh it's the
the consumer of the the service in that
case
um
okay so each coin transaction has at
least one valid mapping
but maybe it has more right like maybe
we can uh um like let's
find one of the diagrams
so um
this is um
two ways of kind of interpreting
a transaction with four inputs and four
outputs
uh this is a mind you a trivial way of
looking at it but like what they're
saying is like here's one way of slicing
up the transaction
uh here's a partition on the inputs
here's a partition on the outputs
uh and the sum of these two parts of the
input and output set correspond and the
same is true for this so
we can define a correspondence between
the parts and uh therefore this this is
a valid sub transaction mapping uh the
sums all add up and uh
and here is another one uh right the the
condition also holds uh because
this is the trivial mapping uh so it
also holds uh in this case
uh so the the um
the first distinction to make is that
this
um
[Music]
this trivial mapping is uh what they're
calling a derived mapping
of the first one
so um the way that you can derive a
mapping from a non-derived mapping uh
it's uh
uh
like think of it going bottom up as you
kind of merge different pieces right
let's say you have a mapping and then
you
blur this boundary and and combine these
two parts and you get this as a result
then intuitively you should see that
this is not actually adding any
uh additional interpretation right like
this is just saying maybe the user who
appears to have done this and the user
who appears to have done this maybe
they're the same user
but there's no additional privacy
benefit from having this additional
mapping in the in the transaction so
basically we should only count the
non-derived mappings
and the non-derived mappings are the
ones that you cannot break down any
further um that
are kind of like elementary uh
so um
if we count only the non-derived ones
right we can imagine that we enumerate
every possible
uh
so
uh we have a set we take the power set
of the set that's already exponential uh
and then we
go through all the possible subsets and
and we
uh apply this kind of recursively so for
every possible subset we say is this a
valid part and then we see what items
are remaining and then we do the
recursively enumerate the power set and
and in this way we can build partitions
and then we can further constrain that
the sums are all correct so
uh this is you know not
computationally actually a
feasible approach because it scales very
poorly but in principle if you have this
naive algorithm
that's able to uh enumerate uh all
transactions even are all different uh
sub transaction mappings
uh even for arbitrary little large
transactions
then what you can do is you can count
right so
if there's an input
i can look at how many
um
uh non-derived sub-transaction mappings
uh it uh i mean
it appears in all of them it must that's
a condition but um i can check
how many times does it co-occur with
some other output
and this also generalizes for input and
output links
and output output links
which gives us this
funny little poop joke
so
inputs
and outputs
uh or inputs and inputs are linked based
on how often they co-occur in sub
transactions right so
let's go back to the diagram and uh i
mean this is the only way to kind of
interpret this transaction that's how
they've set up the sums so because
there's only one non-derived mapping for
this transaction
because input one co-occurs with input
two and output one co-occurs with output
two and alpha one corkers with input one
and so on
uh and there is no other story right
there is no other sub transaction
this means that the probability that
input 1 and input 2 is linked or any
combination of these uh um like blueish
uh uh region they're deterministically
linkable because
there's only one way
but if we were allowed to somehow
interchange these right if they're the
figures here were different and um i
think there's a diagram of that
like two pages down
uh yes
okay so um here we have
one non-derived mapping and another
non-derived mapping for the same
values
and here we can see that
um
some of the uh
inputs and outputs co-occurred
differently right so uh the inputs
are linked in exactly the same way in
this
diagram this means that the inputs of
transaction are deterministically linked
whereas the outputs
like sometimes
they are assigned different
sub-transactions
and sometimes they're assigned the same
right so for output 3.1 and output 3.2
here
the probability that they are
linked to like output 4
output one and output two
uh or to each other
or to the different inputs
um that actually like already spreads
out more right that's not um like a
probability of one for one value but
this is now something that anybody who's
trying to understand is mapping number
one the true mapping or is mapping
number two the true mapping
um
they would have to uh or some derived
mapping of either of these um
that uh
entity would have to uh obtain
uh information that is external to this
transaction right like kyc information
about the history of the coins or or
look at the connectivity of the graph
find consolidations and things like that
or address reuse or some other
clustering
or
yeah uh
use network level privacy leaks but
they would not be getting enough
information from this transaction
specifically in order to be able to tell
uh
what the probabilities
that a priori
output for is linked to output 3.2 or
something
right but um notice that output 4 is
always linked to input 4 for instance
oh no sorry the interchange here but uh
okay never mind you you can get it
okay so
um
[Music]
right that's
uh
[Music]
okay so this is the sub transaction
model um
i think that's pretty exhaustive
[Music]
we've talked about counterfactual ones
i think the next item on the agenda is
like the
results from the simulations that they
had here so let me just consult my notes
um
so
uh
let's jump to figure four
and try and remember why i thought it
was important oh right this is about the
simulation so
one important thing that uh to mention
is uh the way they uh model this
okay so they wrote this
coin joint analysis thing
um
and this works a little bit better than
the naive explanation that i gave
earlier about how you would enumerate
all the sub transactions it still scales
exponentially so they were only able to
actually like
evaluate the results for
uh fairly small simulated uh
transactions but it's still very
instructive
and an important thing to kind of pay
attention to is that they looked at the
blockchain as a whole and
plotted a distribution
of
like
all the different values that actually
appear
so this is like a cumulative
distribution i think this value must be
like 0.01 or something uh like or 0.1
uh there's there's like there's another
jump here and another jump here at one
vtc so it's slightly biased towards
round numbers but overall it's
like the log scale
sorry the x-axis is logarithmic and the
y-axis
is the cumulative distribution so we can
kind of see that this is uh
um
a sort of logistic curve right um
so uh there's um
uh unfortunately there isn't a plot of
the
value distribution
itself but um it
appears to mostly match like what we saw
with the wasabi data where uh it's it's
a rough bell curve with a few like
uh peaks so this is what they're going
into uh right this is how they're
simulating transactions uh to them users
get
um like random values drawn from this uh
distribution
uh and then they have random payment
amounts
uh and
then
uh like this creates a random sub
transaction that that user would like to
perform
uh and the user goes on and does this in
a collaborative transaction so
in the most naive case
uh this is uh what happens right like
uh we're looking at uh three overlaid
plots of uh three sub transaction four
sub transaction five sub transaction
transactions so we can think of this as
you know just the number of participants
uh
and we can see that if we randomly
sample the amounts uh like it barely
helps at all um
uh there's uh uh
um
like the
uh for a four participant coin joint
um
two of the coins
managed to get some ambiguity right
because there's two non-derived
sub-transactions
and other than that like not
not much is going on most of the coins
are actually uh deterministically
linkable based on this result
so um this means that um
and it gets harder to evaluate and even
though you would expect
an exponential growth curve
um the question is okay well how fast
and how robust is this growth
as the number of participants increases
when the amounts are random uh and like
already at five users um
ideally we should be able to do better
than this um so this is uh uh yeah
fairly strong motivation
okay so um
figure three is the one i have on my
notes next so this is also similarly
overlaid
this is about like how long it takes to
evaluate all the different uh
non-derived uh sub transactions
um
as a function of the number of inputs
per transaction so we have a number of
curves in parallel here
and
you can see that the growth rate is
higher when there's more sub
transactions
that uh the y-axis here is uh
logarithmic so
uh the the growth
uh in
the uh evaluation time which is roughly
corresponds to the
um
the search space not it's not the same
value as here right like this is
um
how how big of a space do we have to
search in order to find uh this result
uh but like uh you can clearly see that
this is an exponential growth because
it's uh or even more than exponential
because it's uh
slightly above a straight line on a log
a y log graph
um
okay so um
figure five is also
interesting
uh
oh sorry no we did that one
right okay so uh sorry i i skipped ahead
before
my bad
um
i thought
oh we reviewed the other ones here okay
so um and i already mentioned that we'll
need to relax with some conditions so
here i'm out of stick with my notes so
so keeping up with the
other uh figures
um
now we have to discuss the three
variants of the knapsack mixing
algorithm that they proposed
so
the
first one is uh shown in figure six
for the results of the first one
no that's the diagram we already looked
at
uh okay so figure seven is variant one
okay so what is variant one uh it's this
algorithm here or it's also the the
first algorithm
uh
yeah so um
it's a little bit nuanced but what they
do is they um
some
coordinator like entity has perfect
knowledge of everybody's
inputs and outputs
and also tells every user how they
should split the coins
right so the payment amount is fixed but
every user has a change amount and this
kind of uh oracle coordinator thing you
know whatever it is uh
here it's just simulated um
what it does is it
um uh it looks at the inputs and it
looks at the output in question and um
tries and uh pick a random point uh
right like a random way of slicing the
output so that whatever amount it is
it's the sum of some of the other inputs
in the transaction
um
and this is a little bit naive
but it's already like an interesting
result so like very quickly we see that
even for
uh small sub-transactions
and even for a small number of
sub-transactions right uh already at
four
um
sorry already at uh three sub
transactions we're seeing results are
much better than we had before right
this is already three distinct uh
mappings
um and um
uh like this is an a log scale axis so
so here for five sub transactions uh
instead of the two which would have been
here we're uh already up to like uh
between 20 and 30 i think like 22 or
something like that
so this is a substantial increase
um
but they have done something better
which is uh in the second version they
also shuffle this so the choice of like
how you uh combine different inputs and
outputs
um
uh is different for for every one of the
suggested uh cut points um
so the the results uh from this one i
think are figure eight let me just
double check
yeah
and these are the only two variants that
are shown in the paper but then there's
uh the important one is variant three so
this also kind of works with perfect
knowledge
uh but by shuffling the um
the values um
uh it actually does a lot better um so
um
the
what's displayed in these diagrams is
the number of um
input output links between like the
first variant i think
and the second one
uh
just double check
um
sorry it's somewhere in the
paper itself
um
figure nine
uh
i'm blocking out sorry i don't remember
i i'm pretty sure that this is the
second variant
um
but the the
important thing here is that um looking
at the from the point of view of
individual inputs and outputs
is what we care about much more right
the um this graph shows the number of
non-derived mappings but um and that's a
nice property for a transaction as a
whole but
um
we're much
i or at least i'm much more interested
in this purple line here which is
showing
how many
the
input
input links that were
deterministically
uh
like not deterministically linkable
uh are
shown by this line right so this is how
many inputs
were able to sorry uh how many input
output combinations
um
so how many different sub transactions
did these inputs and outputs kind of
participate in right the other lines are
input inputs and outputs that are
deterministically linkable to to
to each other so this these
lines we want to go down as we see that
they go down here and this line we want
to go up so that ideally none of the
inputs are deterministically linkable
and none of the outputs are
deterministically linkable um
and
if i'm not mistaken uh
even though i kind of lost my place in
the diagrams
the results are not as good for
like unless you do that shuffling
uh and it's also noteworthy that felix
mentioned in the first research club
that the variant iii produced even
better results even though they're
they're not reported in the same way
so what is this variant three um
this one is a lot closer to the
situation that we have which is
uh every user decides independently what
they're going to do and they
um uh
they look at the other users input
amounts and they shuffle them
independently of each other
and basically do the same thing that uh
the the second variant does except in a
way that we don't need multi-party
computations or
some trusted third party in order to
actually build a transaction
the difference is
nothing has perfect knowledge of the
desired output amounts only the
individual users have a knowledge of
their own amounts
but again if we take felix's word this
is um
this works quite well in the same
simulation setting
so uh what are my concerns about this uh
i think this is a very good start but um
yeah any anybody want to um like point
out the problems with what they're
proposing and
oh boy tough crowd
um did i lose everybody
um here
okay um
okay so the
issues that i see uh i guess i'll try
and uh speed this up a bit uh
so uh first of all this is uh
uh really designed for the payment use
case
and it's not really clear how to use it
for
different use cases
the second issue that i see is that this
is not robust uh the the privacy of
individual amounts
kind of depends on what the other users
do uh so they only analyzed the degree
of ambiguity um coming from the non sub
transactions and they kind of ignore the
uh
interconnectivity uh side of of privacy
here
um
and
although the paper kind of implies
in kind of an exponentially improving
security uh i think this is a bit of a
misleading uh like way of of looking at
it
not to fault the paper uh i don't think
it actually makes a claim but um
it's an interpretation that that seems
to be kind of uh
coming up repeatedly uh uh which is that
the computational difficulty of doing
this um is uh prohibitive
um that's not actually the case because
in multiple types of special cases you
can actually
do much better than this naive
enumeration of sub-transactions
and because
as
other users are
potentially hurting their privacy
um their contribution
uh to the transaction also gets
discounted and that
uh results in a an exponentially fast uh
decrease in the uh
in the ambiguity so um
okay
so
i think finally uh
we have a complete sort of understanding
of um
of the model that they proposed uh we've
talked about their
algorithm and and now um
maybe this is the most important thing i
have to discuss today
so this is this idea of uh symmetry uh
between
sub transactions so
um what i mean by symmetry here is uh
like in a mathematical sense the idea
that like there's some invariant that's
uh preserved uh
um
so um
yeah um so let's look at the simplest
kind of symmetry um
so we already saw
um
in the paper
that there's like this way of making
two different mappings um
for some hypothetical transaction
so
let's ask okay well what does it take to
transform between mapping number one and
number two we can see that there's the
number of parts is kind of the same in
both of these there's two and two
uh we also see that the inputs are the
same
across both but what happens is that we
exchange some of the outputs
um
and we already saw in the equal amount
case um
[Music]
a sort of trivial example of that right
like if there were equal amount outputs
here well we could trivially substitute
between them
um
for equal amounts
there's uh it scales with the
number of permutations um
just
uh
yeah kind of an interesting uh bit of
trivia but um
for unequal outputs
um we need to do something a little bit
more clever which uh what they've done
here is they've exchanged
these
groups
right so output
like 19 and 14 together
and
and uh eight
oh wait sorry
what are the actual sums here so going
by the inputs uh
33 and
[Music]
64.
um right so what what they're doing is
they're exchanging multiple
uh outputs for multiple inputs and and
rearranging this side entirely and that
that's a much more complicated
transformation so this is like
a second kind of symmetry between sub
transactions
um so how does this one arise well the
the equal amount one is obvious but this
one arises when
the numbers are uh
like related to each other and in a
nutshell what they're proposing uh in
this paper is
uh if you randomly sample the other
user's inputs
or outputs
you can construct values on the output
side that will lend themselves to at
least being interchangeable with those
amounts that you've selected previously
so if you just do this by construction
once uh you randomly sample you
construct your your value
um
you don't make any attempt to optimize
just by doing that you've already built
like you've you've shown that at least
one symmetry
uh exists in in the transaction um
so that's the uh the second kind right
it's uh um
um
when we exchange um
uh more complicated things um
uh oh i forgot another trivial uh
substitution which is between parts
themselves right so the
uh if the parts were the same size then
uh we could also exchange those uh and
that's kind of the same thing as as the
individual
equivalent inputs or outputs
the
the last thing is
symmetries that kind of um
don't go step wise right like
so
if we exchange individual equivalent
outputs
um like we're never breaking the dif the
definition of uh a non-derived sub
transaction mapping
uh right we're we're preserving that
throughout the process every
intermediate step uh we can also talk
about sequences of transformations that
maybe go through the space of derived
transactions right so like
to do this exchange
from uh like more basic exchanges like
if we think of it of moving one output
at a time
uh we have to break the rule uh that
everything sums to roughly zero
um
so uh a more interesting class of of uh
symmetries arises when we um like allow
ourselves to to do like compound
operations that uh do a bunch of
elementary substitutions and uh kind of
erase the boundary between two parts and
then split them differently
uh because when we do that then we can
sometimes create sub-transactions that
are not possible to
uh derive uh by transforming
uh using only like uh exchanges between
equal valued parts right we would be
allowing ourselves to change the sums of
the the parts themselves whereas when
we're only substituting coins for each
other we keep the number of parts and we
keep the sums of the parts the same and
that's kind of a constraining uh
situation so
um
hopefully this gives a little bit of a
more concrete um
uh idea of of how um
how we can
like if we know that there is one
mapping
and we know some sort of local easily
optimizable property of the amounts that
we pick
can we guarantee that we
allow uh transformations
right can we exploit the symmetry
structure
uh and um
make it very easy to find
transformations that imply the existence
of a related mapping
instead of going
you know the top down route of uh
exhaustively enumerating the search
space
uh if we go from the bottom up we start
with what i know about
my part
of this the true sub transaction mapping
and how do i adjust that
so that i know i'm
helping to
to create a sub transaction mapping
which has a lot of symmetries a lot of
ways of transforming it in in
a very trivial uh composable stepwise
way into different mappings
and
um
yeah i think that's about as much as is
uh
like as deep as i want to go in into
this
except perhaps to mention the the one
thing which is
that um
if we
want to evaluate
this
there's something curious about all of
these uh symmetries which is that
the
the density like how
easy it is to find these
uh for a random transaction
that's
basically something that can be
estimated by
how difficult
subset sum is
um
on random subsets of a certain scale uh
so like if you see that
the subset sum problem which uh very
briefly is you have a set of numbers or
a multi-set of numbers and you want to
find a set a subset of that that sums to
some target value or
in the optimization
framing
that is as close as possible to the
target value so if you take random sets
let's say of size 5 or of size 20 from
from a transaction
and you kind of see is subset some
difficult on this random set
uh at some point you you find a sort of
phase transition
uh
if it occurs it will occur at some scale
uh right like
uh
it takes maybe 20 coins of standard
denominations until on average you find
that
the
the you're in a the dense
class of substitution problems which
means that there are many solutions for
the set and and
[Music]
we can kind of guarantee that
by
using standard denominations as we've uh
spoken about uh before but um
right like by by picking these um
standard values so that they are
uh distributed exponentially with
respect to the same base
what we can
do is increase the economy of how how
difficult is it to make subsid sum
difficult
uh we need fewer values overall in the
set if they all relate to each other in
this way so this means with a relatively
small number of denominations
uh we're able to make subset sum
relatively easy
for smaller and smaller subsets and
if substitute sum is uh easy at a
sufficiently small
scale
then this means that we have an
explosion in the number of symmetries
and this means that
not only is there ambiguity not only
are there more non-derived
subtransactions than one
uh also we should find that the uh
uh
probabilistic links are also uh low in
in those scenarios because um it's not
just the the average case uh that we
would be measuring uh in this but rather
like we're
trying to optimize the individual
clients behavior uh in order that they
um
uh they actually like
that's the thing to optimize in the
online setting right you're
participating in transaction right now
you know what the inputs are you know
what you want to do
um
how can you
make subset sum that much easier uh in
the in this specific context that we
find ourselves in uh if everybody is
doing that then collectively
um
we should find uh enough uh of
the the equal amount um
uh stuff we we should find that the
equal amounts
relate to each other sufficiently well
that the um substitute sum is easy and
uh by handling these two things together
we can
enjoy the benefit of the
interconnectivity graph as well as
protect the
right avoid deterministic links even for
arbitrary
amounts uh within the transaction that's
how we we prevent linking
of uh
input coins um
or try to prevent linking of input coins
going into mixes and hopefully
eventually how we'll be able to handle
uh
private payments directly from coin
joints as well
um
yeah i think that's everything and i
like
hey
sorry i
the exact thing i was
trying not to do by reeling raef and max
into this kind of sort of happened but
i mean we knew what was coming right
i mean yeah i think
you explained pretty well
so is this
is this basically a proof that what we
were trying with our simulations is is
uh
correct even for subset sounds not only
for equal amounts
um
i wouldn't say a proof uh but an
argument but yes that that's a basic
intuition it's uh
um
like
if we do this approach
uh and we there's there's still um
stuff to discuss about okay how do we um
uh
increase the chances that that's the
optimization problem but basically yeah
this is a
logical defense of the approach of using
standard denominations um
trying to account both for the inter
transaction privacy
and for privacy for arbitrary amounts
and trying to
address some of the issues that the
knapsack approach uh i think still has
which is that it's um
a little bit brittle right like ideally
you should not just rely on one
combination of random coins of some
other specific user only to protect your
uh your payment amount
but you should try and
maximize the ambiguity across all of
your output amounts and with respect to
uh all of the other users not just uh
one random thing but i mean that's just
because the
the code in the knapsack paper um makes
no attempt at optimization right it's
just uh uh
a simple simulation so
um i think that's the the bottom line
it's uh like why what is the approach
that we're
um
we we've been gravitating towards for a
while like why do we think it makes
sense uh why do you think this will
result in sufficient privacy uh or at
least why i think that
so
i might be going
forward too much but
let's assume our
last
latest
multi-denomination simulation and
algorithm is
good enough
and i think that's a fair assumption for
for let's say 50 or 100 inputs
but
we can also see that when we go down to
let's say five to ten inputs then
we're not ending up with equal amounts
too much
so
what should be the approach to fixing
that would it be to switch to a
different algorithm or
you think you can optimize that
um
enough
like the main algorithm so even
those cases are covered
where
like very few
inputs are in the transaction
um
what we can do is uh
by
so the first thing to do on top of the
knapsack approach
uh like how do we translate their uh
simple approach into an optimization
approach well instead of only
randomizing one so we've randomized many
times and choose between the random
solutions
uh and then we need some way of
evaluating these but uh in transactions
with a small number of users
if everybody is doing that then the
likelihood that they will pick uh
amounts that are more compatible with
each other and still manage to obtain
some privacy can become higher than if
you just do this randomly
even though block space efficiency would
be slightly reduced in that case
um
so
so yes this is uh um like by optimizing
i think we can also take care of this
kind of hopefully in edge case where we
have very small transactions
but also obtain
more block space efficiency overall for
the same level of privacy which means
like
every everybody should should kind of
benefit even in the large transactions
as well
uh if if we do this on top of just the
the simple randomizing approach
lukas
david
what's your
takeaway from today's session
for me
this is the first time
that
i was going through
this in details
so
i think i have to go through again
but
at least i have a
vague
[Music]
overview regarding this document
so if i find myself in front of a
problem i will
know where to look
for that specific
stuff
so that's my takeaway
yes mine is
more or less the same
and
basically
something that we have been
trying to
discuss but it was not the correct time
is
when to start mixing and what to stop
mixing and
make that
um
or put that decision in a
fitness
function or a cost function
that has to
well
have all this in mind
and
well and we have it it's time to start
coding that by the way
uh yes i've uh i've actually started
i mean the general approach is
all like the jupiter notebook uh codes
at least some of this in the the python
but um
so the the general approach is
demonstrated to be workable and produces
um
better privacy results than we saw for
the just the randomized stuff um
but yeah what isn't done yet is um
kind of like the
interesting stuff that we can perhaps do
later about how to
um so equal amount privacy that's a
trivial symmetry to detect uh we can do
like the the knapsack approach of uh
just constructing some symmetries
uh but if we want to be like really
uh proper about it like we can uh apply
at a later point uh like we can
literally add a
term for the density of the subset sum
problem and i'm i've been looking at
some research papers
uh that do this um
and uh that there's some really
interesting stuff uh so like after
mainnet uh hopefully we can
do this uh even better and um
uh this should have a nice sort of
positive sum effect where everybody
would still be paying the same amount
for the same block space with the same
number of users like so all things
uh held constant
the overall privacy uh and the degree of
the interconnectivity and the robustness
of interconnectivity
all of that would be uh improved by uh
such uh an additional term
but anyway that's that's not for today
or even for the next few weeks or months
yeah just on a general note if you guys
listen back this episode um
i think you can comfortably skip the
first one and a half
maybe even two hours
because
the first
half an hour 45 minutes was basically
bitcoin basics
uh after that
it's
about
um what was it
while
arguing that there are mixing and
and remixing gold outputs is good for
privacy
and
well after that half an hour or 15
minutes definition
and finally the
the final part
which
everyone gets pretty tired by them
probably was the
uh
the the most important part in
terms of that's the
that's the next next step
but even even so
uh this this is more like a theoretical
argument rather than
um
rather than an action of uh
what to do next kind of thingy
uh what i covered today yes but that's
uh i mean for
uh
like what what i actually have uh
in in terms of uh like simulations or
like work in progress is uh
more much more concrete than that uh
so
uh but that that's
also a bit of a long discussion um
there's there's uh
yeah we we can discuss that maybe next
week if you want but um
like the my main
motivation in doing this is like now we
have something documented
where we've uh shared the thought
process uh we've covered um some of the
stuff that was lost in the missing part
of the uh
knapsack uh call and um i think we've
also
hopefully given uh people kind of
a complete account for for the model in
in one place right like if you want to
understand how we've been approaching
the
like
um making the claim that wasabi 2. is
going to be private uh like
this is like you can find all of the
information
that we've used or at least the start
points
uh they're all referenced from here in a
kind of self-contained way so
and i think that's a
great ending
of the live streaming
so
i suppose i'm going to
to close this
and
well just to summarize this is
this session was about making a claim
why wasabi 2.2
should be sufficiently
private or even probably much more than
sufficiently private in my opinion but
all right so
thank you everyone for joining and
and have a good night bye